<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Collision-avoidance on Balakumar Sundaralingam</title>
    <link>/tags/collision-avoidance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Collision-avoidance on Balakumar Sundaralingam</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Balakumar Sundaralingam</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/collision-avoidance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Potential Field Collision Avoidance for holonomic mobile robots</title>
      <link>/class_proj/collision_avoidance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/class_proj/collision_avoidance/</guid>
      <description>Contributors: Balakumar Sundaralingam, Rohith Prasad.
Introduction The use of tele-operated robots in search and rescue, environment monitoring and interstellar exploration has increased in the past years. Tele-operation of robots is a complex task. The operator not only has to focus on the task but also perform collision avoidance so that the robot does not collide with obstacles in the environment. The addition of an automatic collision avoidance system to the robot will ease the operator and allow the operator to focus more on the task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optic Flow based  Collision Avoidance for holonomic mobile robots</title>
      <link>/class_proj/optic_flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/class_proj/optic_flow/</guid>
      <description>Contributors: Balakumar Sundaralingam.
Introduction Optical flow is one of the many ways to detect motion in a video stream. Conversely it can be used to interact with the real 3d world. Exploring this possibility motivated me to see if optical flow from a single camera is good for collision avoidance. The base idea is to have the environment static and the camera moving. This is discussed in the below sections.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>